Avis Berman Research Material on Katharine Kuh
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Avis Berman research material on Katharine Kuh
1939-2006
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Berman, Avis
3.0 linear feet
The Avis Berman research material on art dealer and curator Katharine Kuh measures 3.0 linear feet and dates from 1939 to 2006. The materials were compiled by art historian Avis Berman in preparing Katharine Kuh's memoir, which was published posthumously as My Love Affair with Modern Art: Behind the Scenes with a Legendary Curator. The collection includes Katharine Kuh's files; Kuh's drafts, manuscripts and interviews for her memoir; and Avis Berman's files relating to the book's publication. Also included is memorabilia.
Provenance
The Avis Berman Research Material, 1939-2006 was donated to the Archives of American Art by Avis Berman, an art historian and literary executor of Katharine Kuh's estate in 2007.
Location of Originals
The collection includes photocopies of Katharine Kuh's correspondence; some of the letters may be among the Katharine Kuh papers, Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. The Daniel Catton Rich correspondence is located at the Art Institute of Chicago.
Related Material
The Archives of American Art holds the Katherine Kuh papers, 1908-1994. Also found in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview with Katharine Kuh conducted by Avis Berman, March 18, 1982-March 23, 1983. Additional Katharine Kuh material is located at the Yale Collection of American Literature, Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Writer and art historian, Avis Berman lives and works in New York City. Berman was a close friend of Katharine Kuh's and is Kuh's literary executor. Berman compiled Katherine Kuh's research materials for the memoir that she was working on at the time of her death; the book was subsequently published as My Love Affair with Modern Art: Behind the Scenes with a Legendary Curator in 2006.
Katharine Kuh (1904-1994) was a curator and art dealer born in St. Louis, Missouri. She received her Bachelor of Arts from Vassar College in 1925, where she studied art history under Alfred Barr. In 1928, she earned her Master's in Art History at the University of Chicago. As a graduate student, Kuh developed an interest in modern art, particularly the work of European artists.
Kuh married George Kuh, a businessman in 1930. She and Kuh divorced six years later.
In 1935, she established the Katharine Kuh Gallery in Chicago. The gallery was dedicated to featuring the works of contemporary European and American painters and sculptors, such as Alexander Archipenko, Alexei Jawlensky, Wassily Kandinsky, Gyorgy Kepes, Paul Klee, Gaston Lachaise, Fernand Léger, Carlos Mérida, Joan Miro, Lazlo Moholy-Nagy, Pablo Picasso, as well as Charles Biederman, Alexander Calder, Stuart Davis, and Isamu Noguchi, among others. The Katharine Kuh Gallery was one of the first galleries in Chicago to show photography as art. Kuh held exhibitions for Ansel Adams, Eliot Porter, Edward Weston, and she also showed the photographs of Gyorgy Kepes and Man Ray.
At the gallery, Kuh taught classes on an informal basis to individuals interested in modern art. During this period, she spent her summers as a Visiting Professor of Art History at the University School of Fine Arts of San Miguel in Guanajuarto, Mexico (1938-1940). With the onset of America's involvement in World War II, Kuh realized that the war would curtail her contact with many of the European artists whose works she had promoted and in 1942, she decided to close the gallery.
In 1943, Katharine Kuh took a position in the public relations department at the Art Institute of Chicago. The following year, Kuh was asked to take over the Gallery of Art Interpretation at the Art Institute. Later she was appointed the Curator of Painting and Sculpture; in this role, she developed a close collaborative relationship with the Director of the Art Institute, Daniel Catton Rich. From 1946-1953, she served as the Editor of the Art Institute of Chicago Quarterly.
She left the Art Institute in 1959 and settled in New York City. She served as an art editor at the Saturday Review and World Magazine. She was also an art consultant for the First National Bank of Chicago from 1968-1979.
Katharine Kuh traveled extensively and often wrote about the art of the places she visited such as Sicily, Turkey, and the Yucatan. In the 1940s Kuh developed an interest in the wood carvings of the Indian tribes in the Pacific Northwest. The University of Alaska awarderd her an honorary doctorate for her efforts to preserve the indigenous artwork of the region's Native Americans.
Her publications on twentieth-century art included: Art Has Many Faces (1951), The Artist's Voice: Talks with Seventeen Artists (1962), Break-up: The Core of Modern Art (1965), and The Open Eye: In Pursuit of Art (1971). Kuh also wrote the catalog that accompanied the "Fernand Léger Retrospective at the Art Institute of Chicago" (1953). At the time of her death, Katharine Kuh had completed a final draft of her memoir, which she had tentatively titled, Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in an Art Odyssey.
In 1994, Katharine Kuh died in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The Avis Berman research material on art dealer and curator Katharine Kuh measures 3.0 linear feet and dates from 1939 to 2006. The materials were compiled by art historian Avis Berman in preparing Katharine Kuh's memoir, which was published posthumously as My Love Affair with Modern Art: Behind the Scenes with a Legendary Curator. The collection includes Katharine Kuh's files; Kuh's drafts, manuscripts and interviews for her memoir; and Avis Berman's files relating to the book's publication. Also included is memorabilia.
The Katharine Kuh files contain correspondence; exhibition files; writings and notes; and Kuh's interview with Lily Harmon on J. B. Neumann. Correspondents include Walter Arensberg, Marcel Duchamp, and Edgar Kaufmann. Also included is the scattered correspondence of Daniel Catton Rich with Walter Arensberg, Chester Dale, Katharine Kuh, Samuel Marx, and others. Exhibition files pertain to exhibitions curated by Katharine Kuh for the Louise and Walter Arensberg Collection and one-man shows for Rico Lebrun and Mark Tobey, respectively.
Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in An Art Odyssey contains Katharine Kuh's draft versions of book chapters; her manuscripts and interviews; and drafts of chapters that were not incorporated in the published memoir. Also included are manuscripts for the memoir and an annotated version of Avis Berman's interview with Kuh.
The Avis Berman files include correspondence, writings, printed material, clippings, press releases, and miscellaneous printed material. Files document Berman's activities concerning the publication of the memoir.
Memorabilia consists of a monograph and a memorial booklet.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 4 series:
Series 1: Katharine Kuh Files, 1944-2003 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 2: Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in an Art Odyssey by Katharine Kuh, 1939-2006 (Boxes 1-3; 2.0 linear feet)
Series 3: Avis Berman Files, 1950s-2006 (Box 3; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Memorabilia, 1976, 1977 (0.1 linear feet)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Kuh, Katharine; Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964; Neumann, J. B. (Jsrael Ber); Tobey, Mark
Subjects-Topical:
Art dealers--Illinois--Chicago; Art, Modern; Curators--Illinois-Chicago
Types of Materials:
Interviews
Names:
Arensberg, Walter, 1878-1954; Dale, Chester, b. 1883; Duchamp, Marcel, 1887-1968; Harmon, Lily, 1912-; Kaufmann, Edgar, 1910-1989; Kuh, Katharine; Rich, Daniel Catton, 1904-1976
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Katharine Kuh Files,1944-2003, Series 1:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  This series contains correspondence; exhibition files; writings and notes; and an interview. Included is Katharine Kuh's correspondence with artists, collectors, museums, and others during her tenure at the Art Institute of Chicago and the correspondence of the Art Institute's Director, Daniel Catton Rich with Kuh and others. Letters between Rich and Walter and Louise Arensberg chronicle Rich's efforts to obtain the Arensbergs' art collection for the Art Institute. Exhibition files contain letters, a chronology, notes, list of artwork, printed material, press releases, and clippings; included is an extensive file on Kuh's efforts to organize the exhibition, 20th Century Art from the Louise and Walter Arensberg Collection. Writings and notes include Kuh's article for Vassar Alumnae Magazine; her written reports of visits to galleries; notes on possible acquisitions for the Art Institute of Chicago; and a copy of a transcript of Katharine Kuh's 1984 interview with Lily Harmon on J. B. Neumann.
  Katharine Kuh Files have been arranged into four subseries:
  Subseries 1.1: Katharine Kuh Correspondence, 1944-1982
  Subseries 1.2: Daniel Catton Rich Correspondence, 1946-1958
  Subseries 1.3: Exhibitions Curated by Katharine Kuh, 1949-1955
  Subseries 1.4: Writings and Notes; Interview, 1947-1984
  - Katharine Kuh Correspondence, 1944-1982, 1.1:
    - Abell, Walter - Cook, Gene, 1944-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Duchamp, Marcel - Hess, Thomas, 1944-1954, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Kaufmann, Edgar - Kunstadler, Sigmund, 1953-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Langsner, Jules - Maxon, John, 1949-1959, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Daniel Catton Rich Correspondence, 1946-1958, 1.2:
    - Correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1949, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
    - Correspondence, 1950-1951, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1958, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Exhibitions Curated by Katharine Kuh,1949-1955, 1.3:
    - 20th Century Art from the Louise and Walter Arensberg Collection,1949-1956, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 18-22)
    - Rico Lebrun: Latest Paintings from Mexico, 1954-1956 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mark Tobey, One-Man Exhibition, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Writings and Notes; Interview, 1947-1959; 1984, 1.4:
    - "Explaining Art Visually," Vassar Alumnae Magazine (March 1957), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Reports on Gallery Visits,1947-1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Notes on Acquisition of Artwork for the Art Institute of Chicago,1953-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Miscellaneous Notes,1954-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Katharine Kuh's Interview with Lily Harmon on J. B. Neumann,1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in An Art Odyssey by Katharine Kuh,1939-2006, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 2.0 linear feet)
  This series includes Katharine Kuh's drafts of book chapters, manuscripts, and interviews compiled for her memoir, which she had tentatively titled Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in An Art Odyssey. Also found are annotated excerpts of Avis Berman's oral history interview with Kuh. Files include correspondence, notes, printed material, clippings, reviews, and photographs.
  Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in An Art Odyssey by Katharine Kuh has been arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries 2.1: Draft Versions of Chapters, 1939-2006
  Subseries 2.2: Manuscripts and Interviews, 1987-1993
  Subseries 2.3: Draft Versions of Chapters Not Used in My Love Affair with Modern Art: Behind the Scenes with a Legendary Curator, 1945-1997
  - Draft Versions of Chapters, 1939-2006, 2.1:
    - "Preface and Introduction,"1959-2006, (12 folders) (Box 1, Folder 30-42)
    - "Josef Albers,"1984-1994, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-45)
    - "Bernard Berenson,"1990s (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "Stuart Davis,"1990s (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - "Hans Hofmann,"1990s-2002, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 48-50)
    - "Edward Hopper,"1990s-circa 2002, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 51-53)
    - "Alfred Jensen,"1990s, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 54-57)
    - "Alfred Jensen,"1990s, (8 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
    - "Franz Kline,"1990s-2003, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
    - "Fernard Léger,"1953-1998, undated, (11 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-23)
    - "Isamu Noguchi,"1990s-1995, undated, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
    - "Mark Rothko,"1950s-1990s, (11 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-37)
    - "Clyfford Still,"1990s-2002, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-39)
    - "Mark Tobey,"1962-1994, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 40-43)
    - "Mies van der Rohe,"1990s, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - "Mies van der Rohe,"1939-2003, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - "Vincent van Gogh,"1974-1995, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Manuscripts and Interviews, 1987-1993, 2.2:
    - Manuscript of Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in An Art Odyssey by Katharine Kuh, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Final Version of Sorting Out and Summing Up: Episodes in An Art Odyssey by Katharine Kuh, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Excerpts of Interviews with Katharine Kuh conducted by Avis Berman,1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Draft Versions of Chapters Not Used in My Love Affair with Modern Art: Behind the Scenes with a Legenday Curator, 1945-1997, 2.3:
    - "Alaska," 1946-1997, undated, (5 folders) (Box 3, Folder 11-15)
    - "Central America," 1945-1992, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
    - "Corporate Art," 1978-1995, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 18-21)
    - "Charles and Ray Eames," 1990s-1995 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - "Germany After the War," 1990s-1996, (6 folders) (Box 3, Folder 23-28)
    - "India," 1990s-1992, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 29-31)
    - "La Grand Jatte," 1960, 1990s, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
    - "Mexico," 1990s-1993 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - "Self Portraits," 1975-1990s, undated (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
- Avis Berman Files,1950s-2006, Series 3:; (Box 3; 0.6 linear feet)
  This series contains Avis Berman's research materials related to the editing and publication of My Love Affair with Modern Art: Scenes with a Legendary Curator. Included is correspondence, a letter agreement, writings, printed material, clippings, press releases, and miscellaneous printed material. Also found is Katharine Kuh's correspondence detailing her efforts to find a publisher for the memoir. Writings contain draft versions of chapters formatted on floppy disks.
  The Avis Berman Files have been arranged into three subseries:
  Subseries 3.1: Correspondence, 1981-2003, undated
  Subseries 3.2: Writings, 1990s-1994
  Subseries 3.3: Printed Material, 1950s-2006
  - Correspondence,1981-2003, 3.1:
    - Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Correspondence,1991-1992, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Correspondence,1993 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Letter Agreement, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Correspondence,1994-2003 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Writings,1990s-1994, 3.2:
    - Katharine Kuh Manuscript Chapters: "Sorting and Summing," "Hofmann," "Kline," "Rothko," "Jensen," "The 20th Century Briefly," "Tobey" and "Jensen Revisions," 1990s, (2 1/2" disks) (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Various Manuscript Chapters: "Rothko Quote," "B. Berenson and Germany," "Preface and Donors," and "India and World Corp.," 1994, (4 1/2" disks) (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Printed Material, 1950s-2006, 3.3:
    - Clippings, 1950s, 2005-2006 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Press Releases, 1954-2006 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Memorabilia,1976, 1997, Series 4:; (Box 3; 0.1 linear feet)
  Memorabilia houses a book of poems by Richard T. Cox and a memorial booklet.
  - Many Seasons by Richard T. Cox, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Memorial Booklet for Denise Browne Hare, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 48)